<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Moreno Mancosu</title>
		<description></description>
		<link>/</link>
		<atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>‘New article on "Italian Journal of Election Studies"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://oaj.fupress.net/index.php/qoe/article/view/10749&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Research in political behavior shows that citizens update their past perceptions and future expectations over several phenomena depending on whether their favorite party wins or loses the elections. This bias is explained by different psychological mechanisms triggered by individuals’ attachment and trust in political parties. In this paper we investigate whether such a winner-loser effect conditions people’s concerns about the Covid-19 pandemic. We leverage the occurrence of regional elections in six Italian regions in September 2020, right at the onset of the second wave of the pandemic in the country, to test whether supporting a candidate who won/lost the elections affects (1) people’s fear to get sick with Covid-19, and (2) their expectation about the gravity of the upcoming second wave. Given that the public healthcare system in Italy is managed by the regions, we expect supporters of the losing candidate to lose trust in the region’s ability to deal with the pandemic, hence increasing their personal concerns. We test this expectation using pre-/post-election panel data, and employing respondents from the other regions who voted at a concurrent referendum as a placebo group. Our results show that, while overall concerns tend to decrease from the first to the second wave, for elections losers they remain unchanged. This indicates that losing an election, albeit second-order, can affect citizens’ outlook on future events in domains that are largely beyond political control.
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2021/07/30/ijes.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2021/07/30/ijes.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>‘New article on "Italian Political Science Review"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/italian-political-science-review-rivista-italiana-di-scienza-politica/article/negativity-in-the-news-and-electoral-behavior-between-first-and-secondorder-elections/DB1E20411398D9F59275775093F3F07C&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
The effects of news coverage on political attitudes in election campaigns have been widely studied in academic research. In particular, a fertile branch of the literature investigated the impact of news media negativity on turnout. To date, however, findings are mixed, precluding to state a clear relationship. This paper aims to shed a light on this topic by testing whether negative coverage may affect voters' turnout and to what extent. It approaches this research question by accounting for two different dimensions, controlling whether the interplay of media negativity (press and TV coverage) with the type of election (first- vs. second-order elections) has an impact on citizens' propensity to turnout. We test our hypotheses by taking Italy as a case study because it offers a combination of systemic and media characteristics that allows addressing properly the topic. We rely on four datasets covering the 2018 Italian general elections and the 2019 European Parliament Elections in Italy, respectively, with opinion data (2018 ITANES survey and 2019 ITANES-University of Milan survey) and two datasets measuring media negativity by means of a human content analysis carried out on media coverage during the 7 weeks before the election days (2018 and 2019 ITEM data). Our findings show that individual exposure to negative coverage leads to an increase in turnout mainly to the detriment of indecision. This pattern holds both in first- and second-order elections.
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2021/04/26/risp.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2021/04/26/risp.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>‘New article on "Comunicazione Politica"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rivisteweb.it/doi/10.3270/100310&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Media are known to affect people’s political attitudes and behaviors. The literature has mainly tested whether media tone and visibility affect people’s attitudes toward leaders. However, only a few scholars have assessed these effects by considering the levels of attention requested by different media to understand the message. This paper investigates whether people differently exposed to political communication on television or press might change their evaluations of leaders. Our dataset combines coverage and individual data collected during the 2018 Italian national elections campaign. Findings show that the effect of the press tone is stronger in affecting people’s attitudes toward leaders than that of TV. We also find that visibility has a role only in interaction with tone, namely, the more a positive/negative portrait of a leader is repeated, the stronger the effect. This study suggests that even in information flows where images are prominent, the written word still plays a crucial role in shaping citizens’ attitudes.
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2021/04/01/compol.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2021/04/01/compol.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>‘New article on "Social Science Quaterly"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/ssqu.12907&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Objective
Growing research focusing on citizens' psychological reactions to terrorism finds that attacks perpetrated by individuals belonging to Muslim minorities increase negative attitudes toward immigrants as a whole. We argue that this empirical regularity might be explained by stereotyping, which produces immediate emotional reactions among people holding exogenously positive/neutral attitudes toward immigrants.
Methods
We employ a quasi-experimental before–after design based on the Manchester bombing of May 22, 2017.
Results
Evidence is consistent with the stereotyping effect hypothesis as shown by the temporality of the effect on citizen's attitudes: the effect is indeed strong and significant in the first three days after the attacks for the more cosmopolitan citizens. After four to seven days, however, the effect disappears for every group.
Conclusion
The study suggests that the impact of terrorism on public opinion is consistent with a stereotyping effect and therefore, although immediately strong, it lasts very little in time.
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/2020/12/13/ssq.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2020/12/13/ssq.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>‘New article on "Social Media and Society"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/2056305120940703&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
In reaction to the Cambridge Analytica scandal, Facebook has restricted the access to its Application Programming Interface (API). This new policy has damaged the possibility for independent researchers to study relevant topics in political and social behavior. Yet, much of the public information that the researchers may be interested in is still available on Facebook, and can be still systematically collected through web scraping techniques. The goal of this article is twofold. First, we discuss some ethical and legal issues that researchers should consider as they plan their collection and possible publication of Facebook data. In particular, we discuss what kind of information can be ethically gathered about the users (public information), how published data should look like to comply with privacy regulations (like the GDPR), and what consequences violating Facebook’s terms of service may entail for the researcher. Second, we present a scraping routine for public Facebook posts, and discuss some technical adjustments that can be performed for the data to be ethically and legally acceptable. The code employs screen scraping to collect the list of reactions to a Facebook public post, and performs a one-way cryptographic hash function on the users’ identifiers to pseudonymize their personal information, while still keeping them traceable within the data. This article contributes to the debate around freedom of internet research and the ethical concerns that might arise by scraping data from the social web.
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2020/08/05/Sms.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2020/08/05/Sms.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>‘New article on "Political Communication"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/10584609.2020.1744778?journalCode=upcp20#.XrP6NsuNElU.twitter&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
The debate around political misinformation is gaining increasing relevance among the general and academic audience. If a large body of work is devoted to understanding the mechanisms of diffusion of inaccurate/false news contents (especially on social media), few studies have focused on the individual mechanisms by which people believe in those news. We look at the interplay between two mechanisms: partisan motivated reasoning and political sophistication. While previous literature suggests that political sophisticates are more affected by motivated reasoning, we hypothesize that in the case of character-related misinformation the opposite is true. By using an on-line survey experiment administered to a sample of Italian citizens, we compare the perceived plausibility of real and inaccurate news contents consistent with different political leanings. Our results show that people tend to perceive all partisan-consistent news as more plausible, but political sophisticates are better able to tell real from false news. We conclude that while political information is generally affected by motivated reasoning, political sophistication can effectively reduce citizens’ chances to fall for false information.
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2020/05/07/PolComm.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2020/05/07/PolComm.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>‘New article on "Journal of Modern Italian studies"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1354571X.2020.1723294&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
In 2018 Italian general elections, the Lega has dramatically increased its consensus in the ‘red belt’, the central area of the country traditionally ruled by centre-left parties. Pundits have argued that this performance can be attributed to the new leadership of Matteo Salvini, who changed the ideological location of the Lega by transforming it in a national right-wing party. This article hypothesizes that geographical trajectories of diffusion of the party are associated with the prevalence of a neo-fascist minority present in the ‘red belt’ during the First Republic. By employing official electoral results at the municipality level, the article analyses the relationship between the percentages of votes for the MSI in 1976 and the Lega in the 2006–2018 period in Tuscany, Umbria, and Marche. The neo-fascist inheritance results to be associated with the vote for the Lega only in 2018, after the change in the political discourse and leadership of the party.
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2020/04/23/JMIS.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2020/04/23/JMIS.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>‘New article on "Acta Politica"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1057/s41269-019-00146-3&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Recently, the literature has devoted increasing attention to beliefs in conspiracy theories. Among various aspects of the phenomenon, it was found that conspiratorial attitudes are associated with political behaviour. In Italy, previous research found that Five Star Movement and right-wing parties' voters tend to show higher levels of conspiratorial thinking than other voters. However, the relationship between conspiracism and vote choice remains obscure. By analysing an Italian panel survey data collected before and after 2016 constitutional referendum, we show that the belief in conspiracy theories is associated with referendum vote choices, even when controlling for partisan opinions, leaders’ evaluations, and perceived economic wealth. Moreover, the effect of conspiracism on referendum vote choice proves to be stronger among the supporters of the government, which promoted the referendum. This paper aims at shedding light on the processes of opinion formation and how these are affected by external attitudes, such as conspiratorial ones.
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/2020/01/06/AcPo.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2020/01/06/AcPo.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>‘New article on "Journal of Modern Italian Studies"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/1354571X.2019.1681686&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
This article investigates the patterns of Europeanization of the Italian public sphere during the 2019 European Elections campaign. Europeanization is meant as a multifaceted process. The visibility and salience of the European Union (E.U.) within the public debate is realized by dynamics involving different actors, in terms of interactions, connections and contaminations between different public spheres. The aim of the article is to clarify whether and to what extent the Italian media covered the E.U. during the European Parliament (E.P.) elections campaign and more precisely to assess through which dynamics of Europeanization the E.U. entered the domestic public debate. We relied on data from a human content analysis carried out on 10 Italian media outlets during the seven weeks before election day. Our findings suggest that, compared to 2014, the visibility of E.U. and E.U. related issues is increasing within Italian media coverage. Italian media still maintain a neutral approach to the issue, resisting to Eurosceptic claims from political parties and public opinion. With regard to the Europeanization, we found that media tend to focus on the vertical dimension especially, providing visibility to domestic actors addressing the E.U. and its political actors. Elements of horizontal Europeanization, instead, are mainly referred to events from other E.U. member states, with few connections among political actors. All in all, our results confirm the idea of a growing centrality of the E.U. within national public debate combined with signals of more structured and substantial Europeanization.
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/2019/12/04/JMIS.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/12/04/JMIS.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>‘New article on "Italian Political Science"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://italianpoliticalscience.com/index.php/ips/article/view/104&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
In Italy, the Lega obtained outstanding electoral success in the 2019 European elections, becoming the first party on the political spectrum. Previous literature has argued that this performance can be attributed to the leadership of Matteo Salvini, who transformed the Lega from an ethno-regionalist party into a national right-wing party (Passarelli and Tuorto, 2018). Previous research has also argued that the recent geographical trajectories of the party’s success might be associated with the prevalence of a neo-fascist minority during the First Republic (e.g. Mancosu, 2015). However, the empirical evidence comes from aggregate official results and focuses only on some specific Italian regions of the so-called ‘red-zone’. By employing multilevel models on survey data, this paper tests whether this expectation holds also at the individual level, and in a larger geographical area. The findings show that individual propensities to vote for the Lega in 2019 are associated with the percentage of votes obtained more than forty years ago by the Movimento Sociale Italiano in the municipality where the respondent lives, but only in central and southern Italian regions, in which the Lega was an irrelevant competitor before Salvini’s leadership.  These findings provide additional evidence concerning the ideological drivers of preferences for the Lega.
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/2019/11/29/IPS.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/11/29/IPS.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
