<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Moreno Mancosu</title>
		<description></description>
		<link>/</link>
		<atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>New article on "Territory, Politics, Governance"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/21622671.2016.1265462&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;
And here's the abstract: &lt;i&gt;Local and national effects in the electoral cycle: the case of Italy, 2001–2009. Territory, Politics, Governance. According to electoral cycle theory, in second-order elections small parties are expected to improve their performance, while big parties are expected to be punished. This paper formally tests whether these electoral cycle effects can be considered as solely national in nature or whether they vary at the local level. It tests the expectations in Northern Italy in two electoral cycles (2001–2004 and 2008–2009), with special reference to Silvio Berlusconi’s Forza Italia/PdL and the smaller ally, Lega Nord. The paper analyses electoral outcomes at the municipality level with spatial analysis techniques (Moran’s I and spatial autoregressive model), showing that parties’ support seems to follow a local electoral cycle, partly independent from the aggregate one.&lt;/i&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/2016/12/22/Territory-Politics-Governance.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/12/22/Territory-Politics-Governance.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Article on "European Journal of Population" is now out on paper</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
Very proud of this one. You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10680-016-9380-6&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;
And here's the abstract: &lt;i&gt; Drawing on seminal work by Nazio and Blossfeld (Eur J Popul 19(1):47–82, 2003) and Di Giulio and Rosina (Demogr Res 16(14):441–468, 2007), this paper tests whether the recent spread of cohabitation in Italy has followed the typical pattern of diffusion of innovation processes. In doing so, we contribute to the debate on the determinants of the emergence of “new” family behaviour. Following previous literature, innovative behaviour should spread initially through direct social modelling, i.e. interpersonal communication among highly selected individuals (peer effects). At later stages, the diffusion should spread through knowledge awareness of the innovation, i.e. communication with previous generations (pre-cohort effects), so that also less selected individuals are prone to adopt the new behaviour. In the specific Italian context—a Catholic, “familistic” setting, with high normative pressure and importance of parental approval—we surmise the influence of previous generations to be dominant. We use data from the “Family and Social Subjects” survey carried out by Istat (2009) and apply Event History Analysis in the form of competing-risks exponential models to study Italian women’s transition to cohabitation as first partnership. Results suggest that the most important driver of the spreading of cohabitation in Italy is represented by the degree of its diffusion among older cohorts. However, we find a positive and significant interaction between women’s education and peer effects at the onset of the phenomenon, in line with the Second Demographic Transition (SDT) hypothesis. Cohabitation is also more likely if parents experienced separation/divorce and, more generally, if the environment of the family of origin can be described as “SDT-friendly”.&lt;/i&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/2016/12/03/European-Journal-of-Population.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/12/03/European-Journal-of-Population.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Article on "RISP (Italian Political Science Review)" is now out on paper</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
My article &quot;Contexts, networks, and voting behavior: the social flow of political communication in Italy&quot; is out now on RISP - Italian Political Science Review. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Here's the abstract: &lt;i&gt;Previous research demonstrated that different contextual sources can affect voting behavior. Homogeneous familiar networks affect individual behavior of people embedded in these networks toward voting for certain parties. Moreover, being exposed to higher levels of homogeneity in the geographical place where one lives contributes to developing higher propensities to vote for a certain political object. By means of 2006 National Italian Elections data (and by employing new measures of network political homogeneity), this paper tests, with multilevel models, the hypothesis according to which networks and geographical context interact while affecting individuals’ voting behavior. Results confirm such a hypothesis, showing that familiar networks represent a ‘social bubble’, which limits the likelihood of being affected by the broader context.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Apparently it's freely downloadable &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/italian-political-science-review-rivista-italiana-di-scienza-politica/article/div-classtitlecontexts-networks-and-voting-behavior-the-social-flow-of-political-communication-in-italydiv/3BF41EC9B63378569F3403450B6D9236&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (don't know for how long).
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/2016/11/10/RISP-article.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/11/10/RISP-article.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New working paper (Collegio Carlo Alberto Notebooks)</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
A new working paper has been published in the Collegio Carlo Alberto Notebooks series (No. 464). The paper argues that, to understand the impressive performances of some parties in relative small periods of time, we can employ the diffusion of innovation theoretical framework. A lot of math and nice agent-based simulations included.
&lt;br /&gt;You can download it &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carloalberto.org/assets/working-papers/no.464.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2016/10/14/Carlo-Alberto-Notebook.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/10/14/Carlo-Alberto-Notebook.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Working paper and presentation at SISP conference</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
During the XXX SISP conference in Milan (September 14-16, 2016) I have presented a (very, very) early stage paper concerning selective exposure to populist appeals in social media. The article is available &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sisp.it/docs/convegno2016/125_sisp2016_comunicazione-politica.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2016/09/17/SISP.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/09/17/SISP.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New website</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
Ok, that's pretty embarrassing, but I'm all grown up, I started publishing something, and I must launch my brand-new personal website. After about a half-hour-long beta-testing on it, I concluded that it's more or less readable on Chrome/Ubuntu. Having played quite a bit with the (terrific) &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dbtek&quot;&gt;dbyll code&lt;/a&gt;, I have no idea on how the site works with other OS/browsers. If you find something odd and you're extremely kind, you can e-mail me signalling me the problem. 
&lt;br /&gt;
Edit. I have also created a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/morenomancosu&quot;&gt;Twitter account&lt;/a&gt;, which nowadays seems mandatory for wannabe academics.&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2016/09/01/New-Site.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2016/09/01/New-Site.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
