<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Moreno Mancosu</title>
		<description></description>
		<link>/</link>
		<atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Moreno Mancosu's personal webpage</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
A paper written with Riccardo Ladini. You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/u2rq7&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
In 2018 national elections, the Lega, an Italian xenophobic right-wing party, has dramatically increased its consensus in the ‘red belt’, the central part of the country traditionally ruled by center-left parties. Pundits have argued that this performance can be attributed to the effect of the new leadership of Matteo Salvini, who shifted the ideological location of the party (that now aims at being a national right-wing party), combined with the drop in preferences of Forza Italia, the ally/competitor in the right-wing ideological spectrum. This paper aims at providing new insights in the explanation of these electoral outcomes, by hypothesizing that geographical trajectories of diffusion of the party are correlated with the presence of geographically clustered post-fascist minorities present in the region since the First Republic age. By employing official figures at the municipality level, the paper analyses the relationship between the percentages of votes for the MSI (the most relevant post-fascist force during the First Republic) in 1976 and the Lega Nord in the 2006-2018 period. Consistent with our hypothesis, the post-fascist inheritance is significantly correlated with the local prevalence for the Lega Nord in 2018, after the change in the political discourse and leadership of the party. Empirical analyses provide evidence of our expectations, even when controlling for unemployment rate and percentage of immigrants. &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2019 19:14:21 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/2019/01/05/2018-10-12-soxarxiv.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/01/05/2018-10-12-soxarxiv.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Moreno Mancosu's personal webpage</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
A paper written with Ladini and Vezzoni. You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/0093650218792794&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
General consensus concerning the nature of the relationship between political disagreement and turnout has not yet been reached: while several studies have demonstrated the demobilizing effect of disagreement, others have found no significant evidence for this. Recently, scholars have argued that diversity — a situation in which some people are in agreement with ego and some are not — can boost electoral participation. The present article argues that the insights of previous studies are the result of two differentiated effects that depend on the level of intimacy of the discussants to which one is exposed. By employing a set of linear regression models on Italian National Election Study 2013 pre-electoral survey (N &amp;gt; 8,000), we show that mixed political views among friends boost electoral participation. For what concerns relatives, the likelihood to vote decreases linearly with increasing disagreement. &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2019 19:14:21 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/2019/01/05/2018-08-17-commres.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/01/05/2018-08-17-commres.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Moreno Mancosu's personal webpage</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
A paper written with Monica Ferrìn and Teresa Cappiali. You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.carloalberto.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/no.549.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Growing research focusing on the psychological reactions to terrorism by citizens finds that terrorist attacks perpetrated by individuals belonging to Muslim minorities increase negative attitudes towards those perceived as the ”outgroup”, and especially immigrants and refugees. However, few attempts have been made so far to assess the short-term impact of these attacks. While we know that immediate emotional reactions are deemed to cause stereotyping effects in the days following traumatic events (as a result of coping mechanisms by individuals reacting to a perceived threat), we need more research to assess how long this effect endures. By means of a quasi-experimental before-after design based on the Manchester bombing of May 22, 2017, we ask whether the stereotyping effect occurs, and whether it fades away after a few days. We present evidence consistent with the stereotyping
effect hypothesis, but we also show the role of temporality: while the effect is strong and significant in the first 3 days after the attacks, it disappears after 4-7 days. These findings suggest that the emotional, immediate reactions that trigger stereotyping processes right after a terrorist attack are reabsorbed after a few days as a result of rational processing. &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2019 19:14:21 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/2019/01/05/2018-05-24-CCAwp.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/01/05/2018-05-24-CCAwp.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New article on "International Journal of Press/Politics"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
A paper written with Bobba, Seddone, and Cremonesi. You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1940161218787046&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
This paper clarifies whether and to what extent populist communication could drive different gender-oriented reactions. We adopted an original research design intending Facebook as a natural environment where investigating the interaction between social media users and populist and non-populist parties. Our case selection considers three countries falling into the pluralist polarized media system: France, Italy, and Spain. A human content analysis was carried out on a sample of 2,235 Facebook posts published during thirty days in 2016 by the four main parties/leaders in each country. An original algorithm allowed to identify the gender of users liking each message. We tested whether men tend more to provide likes to messages posted by populist parties, messages published by radical populists, messages containing populist contents, and different components of populist messages. Findings confirm the existence of a gender-oriented reaction to populism: Men tend to support populist actors and parties on Facebook more than women do, by providing likes to their content. Yet the difference in gender gap between radical and moderate parties is not significant. We also found that the antielite component of populist discourse obtains more likes by male Facebook users. This pattern is common for both populist and non-populist parties. &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 02 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2018/08/02/ijpp.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/08/02/ijpp.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New article on "Comunicazione Politica"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rivisteweb.it/doi/10.3270/89738&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Previous studies have stressed that parties that (harshly) blame or criticize the political/economic elite affect citizens' negative emotions and, in turn, populist attitudes and participation. It has also been shown that populist parties and movements massively employ these strategies in order to emotionally affect citizens. The literature, however, pays little attention to the possible effects of selective exposure to these messages. It is possible that people who are «naturally» more prone to feeling resentment and anger toward the elite may actively seek populist parties' appeals that reinforce their opinions and feelings. This study tests this hypothesis for two European countries characterized by the presence of populist parties (Italy and the UK). As a measure of emotional response it employs so-called «reactions», a new feature provided by the social network Facebook that allows users to indicate the emotions that a post provokes in them (sadness, joy, anger, etc.). &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2018/05/22/ComPol.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/05/22/ComPol.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New book out! "Contexts, networks, and the vote"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aracneeditrice.it/index.php/pubblicazione.html?item=9788825512014&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 

Yuo can find the online appendix &lt;a href=&quot;https://morenomancosu.github.io/OnlineApp.pdf&quot;&gt; here &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Contrary to commonly held theories of political behavior in Europe, the political environment, intended as the interaction of interpersonal communication among peers and spatio-temporal contexts, plays a crucial role in influencing individuals' political attitudes and behaviors. This book's analysis makes a number of contributions, showing the effect that interpersonal communication and contextual pressure had on the electorate during the elections of the early 2010s in Italy. By employing advanced quantitative techniques (such as multilevel and agent-based modeling), it is argued that the context - the distribution of potential discussants in the spatio-temporal environment - interacts with the interpersonal networks in which people are embedded, contributing to explaining patterns of vote change and stability of Italian citizens.
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/2018/03/05/Book1.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/03/05/Book1.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New article on "Giornale Italiano di Psicologia"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
A piece I like a lot, written with Riccardo Ladini and Cristiano Vezzoni, only in Italian (so far). You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rivisteweb.it/doi/10.1421/88777&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Nelle survey online, per rispondere alla mancanza di controllo sull'intervistato, si è diffuso l'utilizzo di domande screener per valutare l'attenzione che i soggetti pongono nel rispondere al questionario. Per superare con successo una domanda screener, un intervistato deve seguire istruzioni inserite all'interno di un testo che contiene una quantità variabile di informazioni di disturbo. Mediante un esperimento effettuato in una survey online nell'ambito dell'Italian National Election Study con dati raccolti nel 2015 su un campione di 3.000 individui, si rileva come una larga parte degli intervistati (≥ 50%) non ponga adeguata attenzione al testo delle domande, soprattutto se il testo è lungo e complesso. Gli screener si dimostrano efficaci nel valutare la qualità degli intervistati soprattutto se il carico cognitivo che viene richiesto per superare la prova è basso. &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 08 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/2018/02/08/GioItaPsi.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/02/08/GioItaPsi.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New article on "Politics"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
Italian data, geography, not so related to anything I've done before. You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/0263395717739860&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Context is usually employed to explain voting behaviour, but the way in which it affects people remains obscure. Previous studies have stressed that awareness of the context might indirectly account for political environments’ influence. People aware of their context are expected to be more affected by the relative prevalence of party supporters in their place of residence compared with unaware citizens. By employing stacked logistic regression models (and using Italian National Election Studies data), it is shown that people aware of parties’ settlement in their municipalities are more likely to vote consistently with their surrounding political context.
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/2018/02/07/Politics.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/02/07/Politics.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New article on "Austrian Journal of Political Science"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
New piece on interpersonal communication and influence with a super-cool dataset. You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://webapp.uibk.ac.at/ojs/index.php/OEZP/article/view/1893/1950&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Interpersonal influence - the process by which people change their idea according to the ideas of others - is a crucial me-chanism that forges political agreement among citizens. By using data from the 2009 German Longitudinal Election Study short-term campaign panel, it will be tested how this strategy contributes to changing citizens’ ideas in the proximity of the 2009 Bundestag elections in Germany. Results of fixed-effect logistic regression models confirm the findings in previous literature, showing evidences consistent with influence effects. It is also suggested that the social circle of discussants alters the way in which people are influenced. Propensities to change vote choice, in fact, are boosted by the exposure to disagreeing strong ties, such as relatives and spouse/partner.
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/2017/11/24/Aujps.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2017/11/24/Aujps.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New article on "South European Society & Politics"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
Firt piece on conspiracies. You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/13608746.2017.1359894?scroll=top&amp;amp;needAccess=true&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Beliefs in conspiracy theories have attracted significant international media attention in recent years. This phenomenon has been studied in the US but while anecdotal evidence suggests it is also widespread among the Italian public, little evidence has been collected to assess it empirically. Using data from a 2016 survey, this pioneering study of the Italian case investigates the extent of diffusion of conspiracy theories among Italians and tests several hypotheses concerning individual determinants. The paper finds that conspiracism is indeed widely diffused in Italy. It is negatively associated with education and positively with religiosity, while no correlation is found with political trust. Beliefs in conspiracies are also related to rightwing orientation and support for the populist Five Star Movement.

&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2017/08/13/SESP.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2017/08/13/SESP.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
