<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Moreno Mancosu</title>
		<description></description>
		<link>/</link>
		<atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Moreno Mancosu's personal webpage</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://italianpoliticalscience.com/index.php/ips/article/view/80&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Previous studies have argued that voters’ attitudes of apathy and protest towards the Italian party system, triggered by the economic crisis of 2011, were exploited by Movimento 5 Stelle to increase its support in the 2013 Elections. However, little attention has been paid to the determinants of dissatisfaction that voters showed even before the sovereign debt crisis. In addition to providing a thorough geographical exploration of the party’s geographical scattering (with the aid of global and local indicators of spatial autocorrelation), this article tests the relationship between the strength of the Movimento in 2013 and apathy and protest indicators in the pre-crisis period. SAR (Spatial Auto-Regressive) regression models will be employed in order to avoid biased estimates due to spatial autocorrelation. Results show that indicators of apathy or protest represent significant predictors of the Movimento 5 Stelle’s geographical distribution.
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2019 20:38:40 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2019/07/06/2019-03-14-ips.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/07/06/2019-03-14-ips.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Moreno Mancosu's personal webpage</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
A paper written with Giuliano Bobba. You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0211013&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
A recurrent criticism concerning the use of online social media data in political science research is the lack of demographic information about social media users. By employing a face-recognition algorithm to the profile pictures of Facebook users, the paper derives two fundamental demographic characteristics (age and gender) of a sample of Facebook users who interacted with the most relevant British parties in the two weeks before the Brexit referendum of 23 June 2016. The article achieves the goals of (i) testing the precision of the algorithm, (ii) testing its validity, (iii) inferring new evidence on digital mobilisation, and (iv) tracing the path for future developments and application of the algorithm. The findings show that the algorithm is reliable and that it can be fruitfully used in political and social sciences both to confirm the validity of survey data and to obtain information from populations that are generally unavailable within traditional surveys.
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2019 20:38:40 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2019/07/06/2019-01-25-plos.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/07/06/2019-01-25-plos.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Interpersonal communication, voting behavior and influence in election campaigns a directional approach out now</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11135-019-00906-5&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Interpersonal influence-the process by which people change their idea according to the ideas of others-is a crucial mechanism that forges political agreement among citizens. Previous research, however, focused on non-directional aspects of influence-namely, by testing whether disagreement with political discussants affects volatility in vote intentions. Volatility, however, might be also the result of polarization processes. By using data from the 2009 German Longitudinal Election Study short-term campaign panel, this paper tests influence in a directional fashion, by assessing whether respondents facing disagreement are more likely to switch toward the party that the discussant supports. In order to account for choices’ variations over time, a generalized version of regression models based on a “stacked” data matrix is employed. Consistent with influence expectations, results show that people facing disagreement tend to change their vote intention in order to avoid disagreement with their discussants. This process is more likely when disagreement is lenient (namely, when respondent and discussants vote for different parties that lay on the same side of the political spectrum) and when the discussant is perceived as more knowledgeable.
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2019/06/10/qq.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/06/10/qq.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Political Information Exposure and Populist Attitudes in the «Laboratory of Populism». An Exploratory Analysis of the 2018 Italian General Election Campaign out now</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rivisteweb.it/doi/10.3270/93028&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
The 2018 general elections represented a turning point in Italian politics because of the huge success of two populist parties: Five Star Movement and Salvini's League. Italy was only the last, even if one of the most relevant, manifestation of a general trend: a number of populist formations have achieved electoral success in countries with different economic and political characteristics. According to the literature on populism, the communicative dimension of this phenomenon is one of the key factors behind its widespread success. Despite the amount of scholarships on this, so far little attention has been paid to the relationship between voters' political information exposure and their populist attitudes, and no study has addressed the topic with reference to the countries with a media system belonging to the Mediterranean Model. The aim of this article is to fill this gap in the literature by providing an exploratory study on how the exposure to political information through specific kinds of media outlets is associated with populist attitudes in Italy. In order to do so, the article employs the data collected through a Rolling Cross Section Survey conducted by ITANES on a representative sample of Italian voters (n = 5528) during the campaign for the 2018 Italian General Election.
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/2019/02/25/compol.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/02/25/compol.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>‘Short is Better’. Evaluating the Attentiveness of Online Respondents Through Screener Questions in a Real Survey Environment out now</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
A paper written with Riccardo Ladini and Cristiano Vezzoni. You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/eprint/NQry6Xwk4VAwZ9iHrqe3/full&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
In online surveys, the control of respondents is almost absent: for this reason, the use of screener questions or “screeners” has been suggested to evaluate respondent attention. Screeners ask respondents to follow a certain number of instructions described in a text that contains a varying amount of misleading information. Previous work focused on ad-hoc experimental designs composed of a few questions, generally administered to small samples. Using an experiment inserted into an Italian National Election Study survey (N=3,000), we show that short screeners – namely, questions with a reduced amount of misleading information – should be preferred to longer screeners in evaluating the attentiveness of respondents. We also show there is no effect of screener questions in activating respondent attention.
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/2019/01/14/bsm.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2019/01/14/bsm.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New preprint out now!</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
A paper written with Riccardo Ladini. You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/u2rq7&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
In 2018 national elections, the Lega, an Italian xenophobic right-wing party, has dramatically increased its consensus in the ‘red belt’, the central part of the country traditionally ruled by center-left parties. Pundits have argued that this performance can be attributed to the effect of the new leadership of Matteo Salvini, who shifted the ideological location of the party (that now aims at being a national right-wing party), combined with the drop in preferences of Forza Italia, the ally/competitor in the right-wing ideological spectrum. This paper aims at providing new insights in the explanation of these electoral outcomes, by hypothesizing that geographical trajectories of diffusion of the party are correlated with the presence of geographically clustered post-fascist minorities present in the region since the First Republic age. By employing official figures at the municipality level, the paper analyses the relationship between the percentages of votes for the MSI (the most relevant post-fascist force during the First Republic) in 1976 and the Lega Nord in the 2006-2018 period. Consistent with our hypothesis, the post-fascist inheritance is significantly correlated with the local prevalence for the Lega Nord in 2018, after the change in the political discourse and leadership of the party. Empirical analyses provide evidence of our expectations, even when controlling for unemployment rate and percentage of immigrants. &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 12 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2018/10/12/soxarxiv.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/10/12/soxarxiv.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New article on "Communication Research"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
A paper written with Ladini and Vezzoni. You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/0093650218792794&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
General consensus concerning the nature of the relationship between political disagreement and turnout has not yet been reached: while several studies have demonstrated the demobilizing effect of disagreement, others have found no significant evidence for this. Recently, scholars have argued that diversity — a situation in which some people are in agreement with ego and some are not — can boost electoral participation. The present article argues that the insights of previous studies are the result of two differentiated effects that depend on the level of intimacy of the discussants to which one is exposed. By employing a set of linear regression models on Italian National Election Study 2013 pre-electoral survey (N &amp;gt; 8,000), we show that mixed political views among friends boost electoral participation. For what concerns relatives, the likelihood to vote decreases linearly with increasing disagreement. &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2018/08/17/commres.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/08/17/commres.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New article on "International Journal of Press/Politics"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
A paper written with Bobba, Seddone, and Cremonesi. You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1940161218787046&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
This paper clarifies whether and to what extent populist communication could drive different gender-oriented reactions. We adopted an original research design intending Facebook as a natural environment where investigating the interaction between social media users and populist and non-populist parties. Our case selection considers three countries falling into the pluralist polarized media system: France, Italy, and Spain. A human content analysis was carried out on a sample of 2,235 Facebook posts published during thirty days in 2016 by the four main parties/leaders in each country. An original algorithm allowed to identify the gender of users liking each message. We tested whether men tend more to provide likes to messages posted by populist parties, messages published by radical populists, messages containing populist contents, and different components of populist messages. Findings confirm the existence of a gender-oriented reaction to populism: Men tend to support populist actors and parties on Facebook more than women do, by providing likes to their content. Yet the difference in gender gap between radical and moderate parties is not significant. We also found that the antielite component of populist discourse obtains more likes by male Facebook users. This pattern is common for both populist and non-populist parties. &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 02 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2018/08/02/ijpp.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/08/02/ijpp.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New CCA working paper out now!</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
A paper written with Monica Ferrìn and Teresa Cappiali. You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.carloalberto.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/no.549.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Growing research focusing on the psychological reactions to terrorism by citizens finds that terrorist attacks perpetrated by individuals belonging to Muslim minorities increase negative attitudes towards those perceived as the ”outgroup”, and especially immigrants and refugees. However, few attempts have been made so far to assess the short-term impact of these attacks. While we know that immediate emotional reactions are deemed to cause stereotyping effects in the days following traumatic events (as a result of coping mechanisms by individuals reacting to a perceived threat), we need more research to assess how long this effect endures. By means of a quasi-experimental before-after design based on the Manchester bombing of May 22, 2017, we ask whether the stereotyping effect occurs, and whether it fades away after a few days. We present evidence consistent with the stereotyping
effect hypothesis, but we also show the role of temporality: while the effect is strong and significant in the first 3 days after the attacks, it disappears after 4-7 days. These findings suggest that the emotional, immediate reactions that trigger stereotyping processes right after a terrorist attack are reabsorbed after a few days as a result of rational processing. &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2018/05/24/CCAwp.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/05/24/CCAwp.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New article on "Comunicazione Politica"</title>
				<description>&lt;div align=&quot;justify&quot;&gt;
You can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rivisteweb.it/doi/10.3270/89738&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Previous studies have stressed that parties that (harshly) blame or criticize the political/economic elite affect citizens' negative emotions and, in turn, populist attitudes and participation. It has also been shown that populist parties and movements massively employ these strategies in order to emotionally affect citizens. The literature, however, pays little attention to the possible effects of selective exposure to these messages. It is possible that people who are «naturally» more prone to feeling resentment and anger toward the elite may actively seek populist parties' appeals that reinforce their opinions and feelings. This study tests this hypothesis for two European countries characterized by the presence of populist parties (Italy and the UK). As a measure of emotional response it employs so-called «reactions», a new feature provided by the social network Facebook that allows users to indicate the emotions that a post provokes in them (sadness, joy, anger, etc.). &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>/2018/05/22/ComPol.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/2018/05/22/ComPol.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
